<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached on September the 20. 1632. in the cathedrall church of Christ at Canterbury, at the funerall of William Proud, a lieutenant collonell, slaine at the last late siege of Mastricke. By Francis Rogers, Doctor in Diuinity</title>
            <author>Rogers, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21175</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116095</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851312</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851312</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16583</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10904)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16583)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1186:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached on September the 20. 1632. in the cathedrall church of Christ at Canterbury, at the funerall of William Proud, a lieutenant collonell, slaine at the last late siege of Mastricke. By Francis Rogers, Doctor in Diuinity</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Francis, d. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Norton, for William Adderton, and are to bee sold at his shop in Bethlem without Bishops-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-C⁴ D² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A funerall sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>[Proud, William, d. 1632].</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16583:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16583:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON preached on Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember the 20. 1632.</p>
            <p>In the Cathedrall Church of Chriſt at <hi>Canterbury,</hi> at the Funerall of <hi>William Proud,</hi> a Lieutenant <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell, ſlaine at the laſt late ſiege</hi> of Maſtricke.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Rogers,</hi> Doctor in Diuinity.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2. SAM. 3.38.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Know yee not that a Prince and a great man is fallen this day in Iſrael?</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Norton,</hi> for <hi>William Adderton,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Bethlem</hi> without <hi>Biſhopſ-gate.</hi> 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16583:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16583:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Honoured and VVorthy, Sir</hi> Dudley Digges, <hi>Sir</hi> William Monins, <hi>Sir</hi> Peter Heyman, <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Palmer, <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Wild, <hi>Sir</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Wilford, <hi>Sir</hi> Chriſtopher Harfleit, <hi>Sir</hi> Iames Oxenden, and <hi>Sir</hi> Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Masters.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>VCH Honoured and Worthy Countreymen, this Sermon was prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the Funerall of Lieu-tenant Collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Proud,</hi> our Countryman; who was ſlaine at the late ſiege of Maſtrick. J know not to whoſe protection better to commend it, then to your ſelues, who are all Gentlemen of good worth, and to whom the chiefeſt charge of milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb facs="tcp:16583:3"/>
diſcipline for our Eaſt parts of Kent is committed. Yee were all atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue hearers: may it now pleaſe you to accept theſe my poore endeauours fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, and to cenſure them charitably, J haue what J deſire. And ſo wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all health and happineſse to your ſelues and your families: I reſt, your euer louing Countryman, and faythfull Seruant in Chriſt Ieſus,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRANCIS ROGERS.</signed>
               <dateline>From St. <hi>Margarets in</hi> Canterbury, <date>
                     <hi>Octo. 29. 1632.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16583:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the Funerall of <hi>William Proud,</hi> a Lieu-tenant <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, ſlayne at the laſt late ſiege</hi> of <hi>Maſtricke.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. SAM. 3.38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Know yee not that a Prince and a great man is fallen this day in Iſrael?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE reade before in this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that King <hi>Saul</hi> being dead, there was great warre betweene <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> for the Crowne: <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> claymed it as ſonne to King <hi>Saul: Dauid</hi> did challenge it as anoynted by <hi>Samuel,</hi> and appointed by God. <hi>Abner</hi> Generall for <hi>Saul</hi> his houſe, being rebuked by <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16583:4"/>
for going in to his fathers concubine, tooke it very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignely, and threatned to forſake <hi>Iſhoſheth</hi> and to vnite himſelfe to <hi>Dauid,</hi> for which purpoſe he ſendeth meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to <hi>Dauid</hi> to make a couenant with him: <hi>Dauid</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a wiſe King aſwell as a godly man, thought it no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> neglect ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> opportunity, and therefore he doth embrace <hi>Abners</hi> loue, he entertayneth him royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and diſmiſſeth him peaceably. After this, <hi>Ioab Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> Generall comming to the Court, and whether out of malice, becauſe <hi>Abner</hi> had ſlaine his brother <hi>Aſael,</hi> or out of ambition, fearing that <hi>Abner</hi> might haue his command, or out of affection to <hi>Dauid,</hi> being his nephew, hee is very angry, and telleth <hi>Dauid</hi> that <hi>Abner</hi> came but as a ſpy to watch <hi>Dauids</hi> going in and going out, and therefore it was not wiſedome in <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſuffer <hi>Abner</hi> to depart from him and when he had done ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the King, he haſtneth after <hi>Abner,</hi> who comming to <hi>Ioab,</hi> miſtruſting no euill, was, vnder pretence of friendſhip, moſt treacherouſly killed by <hi>Ioab.</hi> This mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo odious in the ſight of God and man, doth aſtoniſh <hi>Dauid:</hi> for now <hi>Beniamin</hi> and all <hi>Sauls</hi> Alies are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to hate <hi>Dauid</hi> perpetually, yea his owne ſeruants and kindred haue great cauſe to ſuſpect <hi>Dauids</hi> tyranny: wherefore <hi>Dauid,</hi> to cleare himſelfe from ſo foule a blot,</p>
            <p>Firſt, he deteſteth the fact.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he wiſheth a curſe vpon <hi>Ioab</hi> and his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he cauſeth his Nobles to lament, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe followeth <hi>Abners</hi> corps to the graue; he weepeth, and hee bewaileth his death: and hee ſayth, <hi>Know yee not, that a Prince, and a great man is fallen this day in Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words three things are obſeruable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that there is a difference and a degree betweene man and man, in this title giuen to <hi>Abner,</hi> a Prince, and a great man.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16583:4"/>Secondly, that Princes and great men are ſubiect to mortality: <hi>A Prince, and a great man is fallen this day in Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, notice is more eſpecially to be taken of ſuch mens deaths, <hi>Know yee, &amp;c?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt: this difference of man and man, is not in reſpect of our Creator, nor in reſpect of our firſt earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father, nor in reſpect of our matter, for wee are all made of the ſame earth: but it is in regard of the vſe and ſeruice of men in a ciuill ſtate, for parity breedeth confuſion both in Church and Common-wealth, and God is the God of order. See this in vnreaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: The Bees haue in the Hiue a maſter-Bee, whom they obſerue and follow: the Cranes march forth in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly array: yea, among the diuels there is a ſuperiority and an order, for <hi>Belſebub</hi> is the Prince of them, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. There are Nobles: theſe were Noblemen, and there is a degree in Nobility: Theſe were more noble men then thoſe of <hi>Theſſalonica:</hi> For better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this poynt, obſerue foure ſorts of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie.</p>
            <p>The firſt is naturall, which is by birth, deſcending from ancient progenitors, and God promiſeth <hi>Abraham,</hi> that Kings ſhall come out of his loynes. I, but the old Stoickes obiect, Nature is alike to all, ſhe is a ſtepdame to none: are not all borne alike into the world? are not all ſubiect alike to caſualties in the world? and doe not all dye and go alike out of the world? where is then any inequality? Likewiſe the new Switzers ſay, God did not make two <hi>Adams,</hi> one of ſiluer to beget Gentlemen, another of earth to beget common people: Coates, and Creſts, <hi>notos magis facit quàm nobiles:</hi> they make men rather knowne then noble. No more for ſhame: let not that ſin rule among vs which <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>That the vile preſume against the honourable:</hi> They are, me thinketh, as <hi>Eſdras</hi> the 1. booke the 3. chapter ſaith, the words of men in wine, who
<pb facs="tcp:16583:5"/>
neuer remember their King, nor their Gouernours: doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, it is a great bleſſing of God, to be borne of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable parents: for Chriſt himſelfe, though he liued ſo poore, as <hi>the Foxes had holes, and the birds of the ayre had neſts, but he had not where to lay his head:</hi> yet he would not be borne baſe, he would bee borne a Gentle man, he was of the blood Royall, and true heyre to the Crowne of <hi>Iudah:</hi> for hee deſcended from the linage of <hi>Dauid</hi> according to the fleſh. In metals of the ſame kinde (which <hi>Plato</hi> reſembleth to the ſoule of man) ſome are farre purer then are others: In plants there is a great difference of ſeeds and branches:
<q>
                  <l>Est in iunencis, eſt in equis patrum virtus</l>
                  <l>Fortes creantur fortibus et bonis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>If a man haue a Horſe, hee eſteemeth him better, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſire and damme he commeth from. Euen ſo among men, it doth often much auayle from what ſtocke they deſcend: and the Scriptures call men nobly borne, The famous of the congregation, The worthies of the land, The glory of the Kingdome, The ſtrength of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and it was one high degree of ſorrow in <hi>Iudah</hi> her captiuity, that her nobles were ſlayne. But <hi>Generatio op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tima, corruptio peſſima,</hi> beſt things corrupted, proue the worſt: Angels, if they fall, doe become deuils: and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, if they degenerate, become the vtter ruine of the Church and Common-wealth, they are as ſo many Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers fallen from heauen: Hence we doe learne, not with the Iewes to boaſt we haue <hi>Abraham</hi> to our Father, not to ſtand ſo much vpon the blood wee haue, as vpon the good we doe. It little benefiteth a foule riuer to flow from a cleare ſpring. It is ſmall comfort for a blind man, to ſay his father could ſee well: it is no reputation for a deboſhed liuer, to ſay that he is nobly deſcended. If we be the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> let vs doe the workes of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16583:5"/>
and the better we are borne, the better wee muſt liue. Noblemen muſt be like trees planted by the riuers of water, which bring forth their fruit in due ſeaſon, that their leafe may not fall, nor their name periſh from the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond kinde of Gentry is Ciuill nobility, which is by riches; ſhining in the goods of fortune. Hence <hi>Symonides</hi> eſteemed thoſe to bee noble, which in a long courſe of time, were deſcended from wealthy progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: and though it often fall out true, <hi>diuites in arca, pauperes in conſcientia:</hi> Men rich in the cofers, are poore in the conſcience: yet are riches reckoned a part of nobility.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe they make it popular.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe riches are the inſtruments by which vertue and Gentry are or may bee maintayned.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, becauſe being gotten, they ſerue as meanes for vertue and gentry to manfieſt themſelues in action: yet bee not proud of wealth, and thinke not becauſe thou art rich, that therefore thou muſt bee honoured: this is to make men idolaters, to worſhip a golden Calfe, or a ſiluer Aſſe. Riches, ſayth <hi>Bonauenture,</hi> are but as a dogge following two men which walke together, ſo long as the men are together, you cannot diſcerne to whom the dogge belongeth, but let them part, and then the dogge will follow his true maſter: ſo, while man and the world liue together, wee doe imagine riches belongeth to the man, but if the man leaue the world, then riches ſerues him but a dogged tricke, and as the man did come naked into the world, ſo his executors will bee ſure hee ſhall goe naked out of the world, hee ſhall onely haue his winding-ſheete. A man throweth a ſtone into the water, which beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth circle vpon circle, and euery one bigger then other, yet ſuddenly they all vaniſh away: ſo is it with riches, they are quickely gone. As a bird hoppeth
<pb facs="tcp:16583:6"/>
heere, and there, and no man knoweth where ſhe will light: ſo is it in getting riches, which haue wings like an Eagle, to flye away, Luke 12. <hi>Thou foole, this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken from thee,</hi> and then whoſe ſhall all thy goods bee? Striue not thou ſo much to bee rich in wealth, as to be rich in fayth. He in <hi>Plutarch</hi> which had a golden ſhoo, ſayd: I, but no man knoweth how it wringeth me: ſo, to haue a golden purſe, and a galled conſcience, will make all ioy and honour to bee but a dreame at the laſt.</p>
            <p>The world is as the ſea, men as fiſhers, things as fiſhes, none can tell what he catcheth, till his net come out of the water: neyther can we tell vntill we are dead, what will become of our ſoules: then lay up thy treaſure in heauen, and not in earthly poſſeſſions. Purſe-nobility, though it glitter in the eyes of worldlings, yet it is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the hands of fortune, <hi>quae vitrea eſt,</hi> ſayth <hi>Seneca,</hi> a very brittle ſhe friend: See in <hi>Haman,</hi> to day the Kings onely Fauourite, yet to morrow hanged. See in <hi>Gellinor</hi> that puiſſant Prince of the Vandals, yet driuen ſo low, as hee begged a loafe of bread to ſlake his hunger, a ſpunge to dry vp his teares, and an harpe to ſolace him in his miſery. <hi>Bellizarius</hi> that valiant Generall, his eyes put out, would cry, <hi>Date obelum Bellizario:</hi> Giue one poore farthing to relieue <hi>Bellizarius. Henry</hi> the fourth, a rich and a victorious Emperour, he had fought fifty two pitched battels in the fields, yet hee was driuen to that exigent, as hee begged a Prebend in the Church of Spira to mainetayne himſelfe, and could not obtaine it, no, not of that Biſhop whom himſelfe had preferd: but hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Per corpus Franciſci non habebis:</hi> By St. <hi>Francis</hi> thou ſhalt not haue it. Therefore labour to bee rich in grace: <hi>For, not many rich, not many noble, but God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen the poore in this world to bee rich in fayth, and heires of the Kingdome of heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third kinde of Nobility is morall, which a man
<pb facs="tcp:16583:6"/>
doth purchaſe by vertue, and good liuing. <hi>Socrates</hi> asked what nobility was? ſayd, <hi>Eſt animi corporiſque tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantia:</hi> It is a good compoſure, and temperature of the minde and body. <hi>Aristotle</hi> eſteemed him a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which accounted it a glory to giue, and a ſtaine to his honour to take. And <hi>Plato</hi> ſayd he was gentle, which is adorned with his owne, not with others vertues: ſo thou to be truely generous, is to be in life and behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our well gouerned, diſdayning to become ſubiect to vice, or to be infected with bad manners, to be iuſt and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in promiſe, patient in ſuffering wrong, apt to pardon iniuries without reuenge, milde in countenance, courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in ſpeech, ſober in carriage. Nobles may not be like the nobleſt trees, for they are the moſt barren, or without good fruite, as the Oake, the Beech, the Laurell, the Myrtle. They muſt not be like beaſts, whereof the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt are the cruelleſt: neyther are they true vertues of nobility, ſuch as in theſe dayes are vſed, as to dice well, to drinke well, to waſte lauiſhly, and to wanton it ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly: this is the way to bring ruine to your ſelues, for <hi>Now as the axe layde to the roote of the tree, euery tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewne downe &amp; caſt into the fire:</hi> and theſe courſes will bring ruine to your poſterity: for the ſeed of the wicked ſhall not bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned for euer. This morall nobility acquired by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, is like <hi>Abiſhai</hi> one of <hi>Dauids</hi> Worthies, he was the worthieſt of three: ſo this excelleth the other two: but if we compare it with diuine Nobility, it is but as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to <hi>Pharao,</hi> the ſecond in the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The fourth nobility is diuine, to be a true Chriſtian, to be a new creature. St. <hi>Paul</hi> a Iew, was a Citizen of <hi>Rome,</hi> a Phariſe, a great <hi>Rabbi,</hi> brought vp at the foote of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> and circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the eyghth day: being a Chriſtian, he was rap't vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the third heauen, yet he did eſteeme all as doung, in compariſon of being a new creature in Chriſt Ieſus: for
<pb facs="tcp:16583:7"/>
then to bee the true ſeruants of God, exceedeth all other honour in the world: Therefore after <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead, God ſayd to <hi>Ioſhua, Moſes</hi> my ſeruant is dead. If God had ſo much regarded worldly titles, hee might haue termed him another <hi>Noah:</hi> for as when all the World was drowned in the Flood, onely <hi>Noah</hi> &amp; his family were preſerued aliue in the Arke. Euen ſo, when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all the male children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to bee drowned in the riuer, there was onely <hi>Moſes</hi> preſerued aliue in a basket. God might haue called him another <hi>Enoch,</hi> for as <hi>Enoch</hi> walked with God, and was tranſlated from men: euen ſo <hi>Moſes</hi> went into the mountayne <hi>Nebo,</hi> to the toppe of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> and was neuer ſeene more of men. God might haue called him the familiar Prophet, one which ſpake to God face to face, but all this layd aſide, God onely ſayth: <hi>Moſes</hi> my ſeruant is dead: to ſhew vs, that to be a true Chriſtian, and to ſerue God, is moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, yea to bee Gods ſeruant, is a Title moſt dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: for if any aske mee what was great <hi>Alexander?</hi> I anſwere, that while hee liued, hee was a valiant Monarch, one which did conquer the Eaſterne parts of the world: but if you aske me what <hi>Alexander</hi> is now? I ſay, hee is a damned<note n="*" place="margin">This is ſayd according to the Tenent, <hi>Without the Church is no ſaluation.</hi> As for Gods ſecret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, wee may not dare for to meddle with it.</note> ſoule in hell. But if you aske me, what was <hi>Abraham?</hi> I anſwere, <hi>Abraham,</hi> while hee liued, was the father of the faythfull, and now he is dead, he ſtill is and euer will bee Gods faythfull ſeruant in heauen. In diuine nobility, wilt thou know thy pedegree, and thy kindred? Then know, God is thy Father, Chriſt Ieſus is thy brother, the Holy Ghoſt is thy preſeruer, the bleſſed Angels thy attendants, thy foode is more precious then Manna, for it is the bread of life which came from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, of which he that eateth, ſhall neuer hunger, not thirſt any more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, had a monſter brought forth, whoſe vpper parts had a manshead, and breſt, but theſe were dead: but the lower parts were full of monſters
<pb facs="tcp:16583:7"/>
of all kinds, and theſe were liuing: this, ſayd the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, did foretell the death of <hi>Alexander:</hi> So is it in noble houſes. The head with a mans face and breſt, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: If this bee dead, then nothing but all monſtrous ſins will appeare, which will bring ruine and deſtruction to all honourable families: Wherefore let me labour to ſtir you vp to be diuinely noble, and to become true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: and becauſe our meeting is to doe honour to a worthy Souldier, and to a braue Commander, giue mee leaue to vſe for this purpoſe ſome few examples drawne from military diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Souldiers in the field may not vſe their wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons as they will, but as they are commanded. The Musketeere muſt not diſcharge when he liſteth, but when the Officer bringeth him vp and ſayth, Preſent fire: ſo likewiſe the Cannoneere. In our ſpirituall warfare, Chriſt is our Generall, wee are his ſouldiers to fight vnder his banner, our weapons are our ſoules with their faculties, and our bodies with their members, and theſe muſt bee vſed as God commandeth, not as wee deſire. Our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding muſt know God aright, our will muſt chuſe what is good, our affections muſt loue God aboue all: and for our bodies, wee muſt not abuſe them to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the luſts of the fleſh: or make them brewers hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to beare much quantity of wine and beere: but <hi>Wee must giue vp our members weapons of righteouſneſſe to true holineſſe:</hi> our tongues muſt prayſe God, or pray to God: our eyes muſt not looke on ſtrange women to luſt after them: our eares muſt heare Gods Word: our taſte muſt eate Chriſts fleſh, and drinke his blood, in the bleſſed Euchariſt: our hands muſt relieue the poore: our feete muſt carry vs into Gods Temple, and to viſit the ſicke and ſuch as are in miſery: In one word, wee muſt offer vp our ſoules and our bodies a liuing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, holy, acceptable to God, which is our reaſonable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16583:8"/>Secondly, Souldiers execute what the Commander willeth, without arguing and asking why they ſhould doe ſo: as let the Generall ſend to ſuch a Collonell to enter ſuch a breach, to make good ſuch a place, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently obeyeth, for they know that the Generall his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice is for direction: the Officers and Souldiers duty is, to put his direction into execution. Euen ſo, looke what our Generall Chriſt hath commanded in his Word, that muſt we execute, without diſcuſſing by our naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as did <hi>Abraham</hi> in offring vp <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and as the Iewes ſayd vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> Whatſoeuer the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that will we doe. Euen ſo, let vs rather dye, then not performe all God willeth and commandeth vs to doe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Souldiers which beleager a Towne, vſe two kinde of ſtratagems.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they make themſelues maſters of the riuers, they cut off all ſprings of water which ſuccour the Towne, they enquarter themſelues and blocke vp the Towne, ſo that no reliefe of Ammunition, of Victuall, or of men, ſhall any way relieue the Towne. Euen ſo muſt we doe: ſinne is our great enemy: then take heed that we take away from the ſtrength of ſinne, and flee ſinne and all occaſion of ſinne: Adde not to our originall corruption, euill thoughts, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill words or euill deeds. If any man had two ſwords, and being to fight with his enemy, ſhould lend him one: this were the next way to haue his throat cut with his owne ſword. Hence euery one coueteth to diſarme his enemy: ſo muſt not wee adde ſinne to ſinne, this were for to bring finall deſtruction to our owne ſoules.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they doe not onely endeauour to withhold all neceſſaries from the Towne, but they vſe all the means to offend the beſieged: for they raiſe their batteries to make breaches, they make their approches, build their gallies, ſpring their mines, they haue ladders to ſeale the
<pb facs="tcp:16583:8"/>
wals, and all this, to force the Towne. Euen ſo, wee muſt not onely auoyd ſinne, and weaken our corruption, but wee muſt take into our hands the ſword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God, whereby wee may be able to kill all the temptations of the world, the fleſh and the deuill.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Souldiers in the field no more feare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Cannon, then the report of the Musket: as I haue heard it related of that true noble Peere, and vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Commander, Sir <hi>Horace <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ere,</hi> Baron of <hi>Tilbery,</hi> that when in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> a Councell of war was called, and there being debated whether they ſhould fight or not: ſome Dutch Lords ſayd, that the enemy had many pieces of Ordnance planted in ſuch a place, and therefore it was dangerous to fight. That noble Gentleman replyed, My Lords, if you feare the mouth of the Cannon, you muſt neuer come into the field. Euen ſo, oft times men fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers and great temptations: as for to deſpayre of Gods mercies, for to make themſelues away: yea the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill oft times tempteth men by voyce, by appearing in ſome ſhapes and the like. Yet a Chriſtian courage muſt not bee daunted at any croſſes or temptations, but he muſt endure conſtant to the end: for God is faythfull and iuſt, and will not ſuffer vs to be tempted aboue what we are able to endure. Bee we aſſured, all the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that roaring Lyon the deuill, are but like the Frenchmens aſſaults in warre. <hi>Prima Gallorum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aelia ſunt pluſquam virorum, ſecunda minus quam faminarum.</hi> At firſt he doth come on like an Emperour, hee chargeth home brauely: but reſiſt him then: and at the ſecond en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter he is more effeminate then a woman. Euen ſo, reſiſt Satan at the firſt, and hee will flee from you: for the deuill is but like a coward. If a coward deale with a man whom hee knoweth hee can ouermatch, or bee in place where hee is ſure hee may not fight, then none will giue prouder words, nor make more bragges
<pb facs="tcp:16583:9"/>
then a coward: but if he haue to doe with a man, with whom what he ſpeaketh with his tongue, hee muſt make good with his ſword, and if he bee in place where they may conueniently buckle, then none is more baſe or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe then a coward: Euen ſo, reſiſt Satan, and hee will auoyd thee, but giue the leaſt way to his temptations, and then he will fetch ſeuen other deuils, and they all at once will enter into that man, and make his end farre worſe then his beginning. All this that we may better performe, let vs take to vs the ſhield of fayth, and pray to God, that all our thoughts, words, and deeds, may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, continued, and ended, to his glory. And ſo I paſſe to the ſecond thing. <hi>Princes and great men are ſubiect to mortality.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Pallida mors aequo pulſat pede</l>
               <l>Pauperum domos, Regum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> turres.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Death ſeazeth on the King in his Palace, as well as on the begger in his cottage. It is determined for all men to dye once. Death, Gods Baylife, returneth not his writ with a <hi>Non eſt inuentus in baliuanostra:</hi> but death brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>corpus cum cauſa</hi> to the King of heauens bench. A King may loue his friends, and aduance his followers to honour, but to adiourne death, or to fill the empty veines with liuely blood, or the dry bones with mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or redeeme life from the power of the graue: in theſe things, nor <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor any other is a King, 2. <hi>Reg.</hi> 5. 7. <hi>Am I God,</hi> ſayth the King of <hi>Iſrael, to kill, and to giue life, or can I heale Naamans le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Vſes of this Doctrine are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, let euery man perſwade himſelfe that he ſhall dye. This may ſeeme a paradox: for it any ſo ſottiſh as to imagine he ſhall neuer dye? Beloued, bee not deceiued, I am perſwaded, few men doe dreame of their owne death: for there is none ſo old, but thinketh he may liue one yeere longer, and then another, though in generall
<pb facs="tcp:16583:9"/>
wee ſay all ſhall dye: yet in numbering our particular liues, we thinke our ſelues ſhall neuer dye. Two ſhips meete on the ſea, they in eyther ſhip thinke themſelues ſtand ſtill, and the other to bee ſwift of ſayle, whereas both ſayle, though the one faſter then the other. Euen ſo, men are as ſhips: ſee we an old man with a ſtaffe in his hand ſtooping downeward? Alaſſe, poore old man, ſay we, hee cannot liue long. Heare wee a paſſing-bell? Oh one is going out of the world. Viſit wee a ſicke friend? We thinke he can hardly liue till morning. Thus we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, all other men are dying, but we ſtand ſtill: whereas alaſſe, they may goe a little before, and wee are ſure to follow after.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let this teach vs to prepare our ſelues to dye, that if death be ſudden to vs in regard of expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet death may neuer be ſudden to vs in regard of preparation: death is like the Baſiliske: It is reported, if a Baſiliske firſt ſee a man before the man ſee him, that then he killeth the man: but if a man firſt ſee a Baſiliske, then the Baſiliske dieth. Thus is it with death: If death firſt lay hold on a man before he is prepared to dye, then death killeth that man, body and ſoule for euer: but if a man firſt looke on death, and euery day prepare to dye, then death is but an entrance into euerlaſting happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>It is a worthy thing which hath beene related to me, of that braue ſouldier, of a noble Family, Sir <hi>Iohn Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> who receiuing a mortall wound in the Iland of <hi>Rees,</hi> and being aduiſed not to feare death, but to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for another world, he anſwered: I thanke God, I feare not death, and theſe thirty yeeres together, I neuer aroſe at the morning, that euer I made account to liue till night: ſo let euery true Chriſtian euery day when he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waketh, commend himſelfe to Gods protection, whether he liue or dye, and at the euening none knoweth, if That nights bed ſhall be his graue, or That nights ſleepe ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:16583:10"/>
be his death: therefore before his eyes doe ſleepe, or his eyelids ſlumber, or the temples of his head take reſt, make his peace with God for all ſinnes: that whether he liue or dye, hee may liue and dye to the Lord, and Ieſus Chriſt may be to him aduantage. And ſo I paſſe to the laſt thing. Notice is to be taken of a great mans death. <hi>Know ye not, &amp;c.</hi> The death of a great man, and of a meane man is like the report of a Cannon and of a Musket: a Cannon is heard many miles, but a Musket for a little ſpace. So, if a great man dye, all men ſpeake of it: as, ſuch an Earle, ſuch a Biſhop, ſuch a Commander is dead. But if a poore man, or a common ſouldier dye, few of his neyghbours and friends accompany him to the graue, and there is an end of him. But i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a great man dye, which is able to doe his Country ſeruice, notice ſhall bee taken of it to lament his death: ſo is <hi>Abner</hi> heere bewayled both of King and people. In <hi>Eſay</hi> the 3. chapter, God threatneth it as a plague, <hi>He will take away the strong man, and the man of warre.</hi> Therefore as <hi>Lament.</hi> 1.15.16. <hi>The Lord hath tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vnder foote all the valiant men in the middeſt of mee: for this thing I weepe, mine eye, euen mine eye casteth out water, becauſe the Comforter which ſhould refreſh my ſoule, is farre from me.</hi> God taketh away good men, and great men in mercy and in iudgement. In mercy, when God taketh away a bad Prince, and giueth a better, as hee tooke <hi>Saul,</hi> and gaue <hi>Dauid.</hi> Hee tooke away from this land Queene <hi>Mary</hi> and gaue vs Queene <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Or when God taketh away a good Prince, and giueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother good one in his place. Thus he tooke away <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and gaue <hi>Ioſhua:</hi> thus from vs hee tooke away King <hi>Iames,</hi> and gaue vs King <hi>Charles,</hi> whom God long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue among vs: God taketh away great men in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eyther when he taketh good Gouernors, and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vp none in their ſtead. Thus when all the Rulers were dead which knew <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> God gaue the Iewes no Rulers: for in thoſe dayes there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:16583:10"/>
but euery one did what ſeemed beſt in his owne eyes. Or elſe God taketh away good Rulers, and rayſeth vp bad, as he tooke away <hi>Samuel,</hi> and gaue <hi>Saul.</hi> Let vs conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if within theſe few yeeres God hath not taken away many of our braue Gentiles, and worthy Souldiers: but where haue we a ſucceeding generation? What are our Ships without Saylors? What are our Gunnes without men? What are our men without diſcipline? And how can we haue diſcipline, without braue Commanders, and experienced Souldiers? <hi>Philip,</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted the <hi>Athenians</hi> happy, becauſe they were able euery yeere, to ſend out ten worthy Commanders, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as he onely had <hi>Parmenio.</hi> Hence did this Nation floriſh heretofore, and was a terrour to all Nations. Yea <hi>Charles</hi> the eighth of <hi>France</hi> attired his ſouldiers like Engliſhmen to make them more fearefull to his Rebels: but now alas, of late God hath not gone forth with our armies, but for our ſinnes he hath made vs an hiſſing and a by word to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people. Oh, now <hi>Abner</hi> hath leaue to dye, and men of action by the ſword neuer leſſe regarded, neuer better ſpared. Well, bleſſed be God for our peace, and pray we all for the peace of our <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> Let them proſper which loue it: yet let not vs be ſecure. The ſons of <hi>Zeruiah</hi> may be too mighty for vs, though our enemies abroad do ſleep, and the Papiſts at home are not plotting treaſons: yet the deuill all this time may rocke the cradle, and God may one day ſuffer the child to awake: &amp; therefore let not ſo many <hi>Abners,</hi> nor this worthy <hi>Abner</hi> before vs dye, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſence of a publike loſſe, and an vniuerſall condolment of the whole State. For ſo ſaith my text, <hi>Know yee not that a Prince, &amp;c?</hi> A Prince, that is, a prime man, a principall Commander, a valiant Souldier, and a worthy Warrier. And hauing finiſhed my text, giue me leaue to ſpeake of this preſent occaſion. <hi>Ptolomeus</hi> asketh a queſtion, What courſe men noble in birth, &amp; quality of mind, yet oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with pouerty, ſhould take to liue by, and to be fruitfull members in the Commonwealth? He anſwerd, They may in
<pb facs="tcp:16583:11"/>
no wiſe practiſe any baſe or mechanicall trade, but they muſt addict themſelues, eyther to the ſeruice of their Prince, or bee Prieſts of Gods Altar, or elſe giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to chiualry, and a military life. This latter kinde of calling, our Countryman this noble Commander vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke. What, to be a ſouldier?</p>
            <q>Nulla fides, pietaſque viris qui bella ſequuntur.</q>
            <p>There is neyther fayth nor piety in men of warre which liue by their ſword: But Gods Word will gaineſay this. <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faythfull, was a ſouldier, when with 300. armed men he aroſe and reſcued <hi>Lot,</hi> and the Kings which were taken priſoners. <hi>Iacob</hi> his grandchild was a warrier: for, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.22. hee gaue to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aboue his brethren, which, ſayd he, I got out of the hands of the Amorites by my ſword and by my bow. <hi>Dauid</hi> a godly man was a ſouldier, for God did teach his hands to warre, and his fingers to fight, and he entred the liſts and fought a priuate duell with great <hi>Goliah,</hi> that monſter of the Philiſtines, and he did cut off his head with his owne ſword. In the new Teſtament, the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turion was ſo beleeuing, as Chriſt ſayd, <hi>Verily I haue not found ſo great fayth, no not in Iſrael.</hi> And <hi>Cornelius,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Italian band, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. was a deuout man, who feared God, with all his houſehold, which did giue much almes to the people, and prayed God continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally. Thus we ſee, ſouldiers may be, and often are, very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious. And they are neceſſary members for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth. Hence <hi>Gabriel Simon</hi> did picture <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> ſtanding vpon a Globe of the world, holding in his left hand a booke, &amp; in his right hand a ſword drawne, with this Motto: <hi>Ex vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Caeſar:</hi> to ſhew that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire was gotten, and held by armes and good letters. And the great Turke, going into his Oratory to performe his deuotions, the Taleſman with a loud voyce willeth him to remember, that as the Empire was gotten by iuſtice, and military diſcipline, ſo it muſt be mayntayned by the
<pb facs="tcp:16583:11"/>
ſame weapons: for as in the body naturall, if the head ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe neuer ſo well, the eye ſee neuer ſo clearely, and the toung ſpeake neuer ſo pleaſingly, yet if the armes be dead or diſioynted, the body can neyther offend other, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it ſelfe. Euen ſo, in the body politicke: If the head, that is, the King, by his Councell aduiſe neuer ſo well: if the eyes, that is, the reuerend Biſhops and Cleargy, ſee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo well, and expell all miſts of error, ſuperſtition and idolatry, if the tongue, that is, the learned Iudges and Lawyers adminiſter iuſtice neuer ſo vprightly: yet if the Strong men, the men of warre, which are the armes of the Kingdome, be dead, or diſarmed, we can neyther offend any other, nor defend our ſelues from the inuaſion of an enemy: All which doe ſhew the neceſſity of the Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble profeſſion of a Souldier. To come now to my ſubiect: This valiant Souldier firſt went for his Countries ſeruice, <hi>Portugall</hi> voyage. Then he ſerued in the wars of <hi>Brittany.</hi> Thirdly, He went <hi>Cales</hi> voyage. Next the Iland voyage. Fiftly, He went into <hi>Ireland,</hi> where he was Collonell to a troope of Horſe, which being caſſier'd, he was made Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant to a Foote-company. After all theſe trauels, &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, he went to <hi>Oſtend,</hi> the moſt famous ſiege that euer was, or I thinke, euer will be. The enemy valiantly aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the beſieged valiantly repulſed them. The then Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, the honour of our Nation in this latter age, Noble Sir <hi>Francis Vere,</hi> employed him being but a priuate Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, in a ſally: in which he got the firſt badge of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, being ſhot into the thigh with a musket bullet. And the Generall obſeruing his valour, and his ſtout and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creete anſwere, tooke ſuch liking of him, as ſhortly after his returne he made him a Lieutenant, and in a little ſpace after, he made him a Chiefetaine, we ſay a Captaine, which hee alwaies to his dying day would acknowledge with a moſt thankefull mind, to be the ground of all his honour and fortune. And ſuch was his fidelity euer after, to that noble Generall, as he would not endure any man to ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:16583:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
baſely of him, or in the leaſt meaſure to detract from his worth. Hauing gotten this honour, he ſo carried himſelfe, for valour, for diligence, for inſight in his Office, as that the late Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> of famous memory, and the now illuſtrious and victorious Prince, and all the army no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his worth and merit. And ſtill he aduanced himſelfe to higher place, being made a Seriant Maior of a Regiment, and after that a Lieutenant Collonell.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <l>Degeneres animos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rguit, heu quibus ille</l>
                  <l>Ia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>us vemis, quae bella exhauſta canebat,</l>
               </q>
ſayth Queene <hi>Dido</hi> of braue <hi>Aeneas:</hi> ſo this worthy Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine neuer harboured the leaſt thought of baſe cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe in his breſt. How many dangers? How many bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailes? How many skirmiſhes? How many ſieges hath he paſt thorow? yea, with loſſe of blood, but alwaies with gaine of honour. I may ſay of him, as is ſayd of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes, Omnia pericula intrepide pertranſit,</hi> he ranne thorow all dangers with an vndanted reſolution: and as <hi>Seneca</hi> of another, <hi>fuit vir vere fortis, gloriam maluit quam vitam,</hi> he was a man truely valorous, hee had rather maintayne his honour then to preſerue his life. And which is more, he did not abuſe Gods bleſſings, as many doe, to ryot and waſte, but knowing hee is worſe then an Infidell, which prouideth not for his family: yet abhorring a baſe and ſordid courſe, he liued in a fit equipage for his place and dignity, and yet left a large poſſeſſion behinde him for his poſterity. So I may truely ſay of him, <hi>Ille ſuis maioribus virtute praeterit,</hi> hee ſurpaſſed all his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in vertue and valour, and withall <hi>non fuit finis, ſed principium familiae:</hi> Hee was not the end, but the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and foundation of his family. Hee hath ſo rayſed his houſe, as that his Heire may liue nobly, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort himſelfe with the prime Gentlemen of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> when he ſaw great <hi>Alexanders</hi> Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that it was written on his Trophee, That at 32.
<pb facs="tcp:16583:12"/>
yeeres of age, he had conquered the Eaſterne parts of the world: did preſently weepe, to thinke, that himſelfe being thirty foure yeeres of age, had done no memorable Act, to purchaſe honour to his Country, or to himſelfe. And ſo me thinkes, this patterne of true Nobility before vs, ſhould ſtirre vp the braue ſpirits of our Gentlemen: ſpecially, the yonger brothers of families, not to ſpend their dayes in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in a Tauerne, or the like: but they ſhould endeuour by ſome vertuous profeſſion to augment their fortunes, and to adde luſtre to their Families.</p>
            <p>But to goe forward, <hi>Abner</hi> in my text did fall: ſo did this our <hi>Abner:</hi> but as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayd, <hi>Dyed Abner as a foole? thy hands were not bound, nor thy feete tyed with fetters of braſſe.</hi> So, did this braue Commander dye like a foole? as a baſe man that is whipped in the ſtocks? or as a malefactor which is led bound to execution? No ſurely, but as we ſay, <hi>O portet imperatorem mori ſtantem:</hi> An Emperour ſhould dye ſtanding. The comfortableſt bed for a Preacher to dye in, is the Pulpit. So, a Souldier ſhould dye honorably in the field. And thus did this noble Leader dye in the bed of honour, in the field, in the execution of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and the face of his enemies. And as <hi>Dauid,</hi> the Nobles, and the people, buried <hi>Abner</hi> nobly, and mourned for him: ſo the Prince, and the whole Army bewailed this Souldiers death: and they did burie his bowels there, in an honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner. His body is brought to bee interred in his owne Citty, and Country. And as when King <hi>Ioſiah</hi> was buried, all <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> mourned, and came to his buriall: Euen ſo,
<q>Sic enim paruis componere magna ſolebam.</q>
all the Country round about, of the prime ranke, for Knights, Cleargy, and Gentlemen, with the graue Citizens and others came to performe their laſt duety of ciuill humanity, and Chriſtian charity, to his deceaſed corps, deſiring to giue him that honour, which while he liued, he worthily purchaſed to himſelfe by his valour. I, but all this may be ſaid of an Infidell,
<pb facs="tcp:16583:13"/>
as of <hi>Alexander, Caeſar, Scipio, Hanibal.</hi> Marke then for his ſoule, and for him, a true Chriſtian Noble. His cuſtome, when he came into England was obſerued, ſtill on the Sabbath, and on the Lecture daies, to frequent Gods Temple, for to heare Gods Word: and where hee liued, I am credibly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by diuers, that twice euery day in his priuate cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, hee did vſe to pray heartily, and feruently to God on his knees, both for the forgiueneſſe of his owne ſins, and for a bleſſing vpon his family: and he did dayly vſe to reade in the Bible, and in other good bookes. But ſome weeke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, he was farre more deuout, and giuen to holy exerciſes then ordinary.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sic vbi fata vocant, vdis abiectus in herbis,</l>
               <l>Ad vada Maeandri concinit albus olor.</l>
            </q>
            <p>As the Swan, ſo this Chriſtian noble Lieutenant Collonell, ready to leaue the world, did ſing more ſweetly, then euer he did before. And he carried into the army, not only ſword and ſpeare, weapons for a Souldier: but for his Chriſtian warfare, he had his Bible, his Prayer booke, and other Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of holy deuotion. What ſhould I ſay more? He which in his life-time gaue ſuch a teſtimony of a liuely, and of an vnſayned repentance: and he which dyed in the quarrell of Gods true Religion, and for his Countries firme Alies: I doubt not but in the Canon of charity, I may apply to him the ſaying of S. <hi>Paul, He hath fought a good fight, he hath fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed a good courſe.</hi> Therefore hee is now crowned with glory in the Kingdome of Heauen: where wee leaue his ſoule ſinging with the heauenly Quire, <hi>Amen, Halelluiah,</hi> glory, honor, and maieſty be giuen to God, &amp; to the Lambe that ſitteth vpon the Throne for euermore. And we commit his body to the graue to ſleepe and reſt in peace, till the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reſurrection at the laſt day: where they which haue done euill, ſhall ariſe to euerlaſting damnation, and they which haue done well, ſhall ariſe to euerlaſting ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Now, God of his mercy make vs partakers of this latter Reſurrection, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16583:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
